Guide to the William Wallace Tooker papers, [18--]-1917.
Tooker, William Wallace papers, [18--]-1917
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
William Wallace Tooker papers, [18--]-1917.
9187
William Wallace, Tooker 1848-1917.
1 cubic ft. (45 folders; 7 volumes).
Correspondence, Diaries, Manuscripts
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Correspondence, memoranda, notes, and other papers, concerning Indian place names on Long Island, N.Y., Coastal Algonquian ethnology, ethnohistory, and linguistics. Notes investigate name origins and discuss how they derive from native languages. Other notes include analysis of early American texts in native languages. Extracts made from Indian land deeds and notes discussing land boundaries also included. Index cards for all the items included.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
William Wallace Tooker once was widely recognized as one of his era's leading specialists in Coastal Algonquian culture, history and place names. A prolific writer, he published 12 books, some 50 pamphlets and over 100 articles between 1888 and 1911. During his life and for many years thereafter, nearly every scholar interested in one aspect or another of Coastal Algonquian life routinely consulted his work.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Correspondence, memoranda, notes, and other papers, concerning Indian place names on Long Island, N.Y., Coastal Algonquian ethnology, ethnohistory, and linguistics. Notes investigate name origins and discuss how they derive from native languages. Other notes include analysis of early American texts in native languages. Extracts made from Indian land deeds and notes discussing land boundaries also included. Index cards for all the items included.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Tooker, William Wallace,1848-1917.; Ackerly, O. B.; Bicknell, Thomas Williams, 1834-1925.; Canfield, James A.; Eliot, John, 1604-1690.; Gardiner, John Lyon.; Gib, Andrew.; Horton, Azariah.; Howell, George Rogers, 1833-1899.; Jefferson, Thomas, 1743-1826.; Pelletreau, William S.(William Smith), 1840-1918.; Smith, John, 1580-1631.; Strachey, William, 1572?-1621.; Tooker, William Wallace, 1848-1917.; Trumbull, J. Hammond(James Hammond), 1821-1897.; Williams, Roger, 1604?-1683.; Wright, Harry Andrew.; Huntington Free Library.; Society in Scotland for Propagating Christian Knowledge.
Subjects:
Indians of North America.; Indians of North America--Massachusetts.; Indians of North America--New York (State).; Indians of North America--Rhode Island.; Indians of North America--Claims.; Indians of North America; Indians of North America--Land tenure.; Indian land transfers.; Indian title.; Algonquian Indians.; Algonquian languages.; Delaware Indians.; Delaware language.; Kuskarawaoke Indians.; Massachuset Indians.; Massachuset language.; Montauk Indians.; Nowedonah Indians.; Pamunkey Indians.; Poosepatuck Indians.; Powhatan Indians.; Powhatan language.; Rappahannock Indians.; Shinnecock Indians.; Susquehanna Indians.; Unkechaug Indians.; Names, Geographical.; Names, Geographical--New York. (N.Y.)--Brooklyn.; Names, Geographical--Chesapeake Bay (Md. and Va.); Names, Geographical--Virginia--Chickahominy.; Names, Geographical--New York. (State)--Long Island.; Names, Geographical--New York. (N.Y.)--Manhattan.; Names, Geographical--Massachusetts--Martha's Vineyard.; Names, Geographical--New York. (State)--Patchogue.; Names, Geographical--New York. (State)--Southampton.; Names, Geographical--New York. (State)--Suffolk County.; Names, Geographical--Pennsylvania--Susquehanna.; Names, Geographical--Virginia.; Names, Indian--North America.; Bible.--Massachuset.--Eliot
Places:
Brookhaven (N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Chesapeake Bay (Md. and Va.); East Hampton (N.Y.); Gardiner's Island (N.Y.); Huntington (N.Y.); Little Neck (New York, N.Y.); Long Island (N.Y.); Manhattan (New York, N.Y.); Martha's Vineyard (Mass.); Patchogue (N.Y.); Southampton (N.Y.); Southold (N.Y.); Suffolk County (N.Y.); Virginia.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
William Wallace Tooker: Pioneer Algonkinist, 1848-1917, by Robert S. Grumet
William Wallace Tooker once was widely recognized as one of his era's leading specialists in Coastal Algonquian culture, history and place names. A productive and prolific writer, he published 12 books, some 50 pamphlets and over 100 articles between 1888 and 1911. During his life and for many years thereafter, nearly every scholar interested in one aspect or another of Coastal Algonquian life routinely consulted his work. Community leaders and businessmen beat paths to his door in search of appropriate Indian names for their enterprises or meanings of local place names. As late as the 1960's, most publishers printing works of Long Island history used Tooker's studies as the standard against which newer efforts were measured.
Today, few people remember the man or his work. Only one of his books, the last and most comprehensive of his works, Indian Place Names on Long Island, is still in print. The rest of his writings were published in limited editions, appeared in local or now defunct newspapers and journals, or remain in manuscript form. Only a few local libraries and some larger repositories, such as the New York Public Library, the Library of Congress and the Newberry Library, possess extensive collections of Tooker's publications. The John Jermain Memorial Library, located in his hometown of Sag Harbor, Long Island, holds some of his scholarly correspondence and a number of manuscripts written from 1887 to 1915.
The largest and most extensive collection of Tooker's published and unpublished work today is maintained by the Library. At one time available only to specialists able to visit the Huntington Free Library, their production of a microfilm edition of the Tooker manuscript collection holdings made this important body of material accessible to wider reading public for the first time. These manuscripts contain a wealth of unpublished data on Coastal Algonquian culture history and philology. They also provide insights into the life and times of a significant and all but forgotten pioneer Algonkinist during the formative years of modern Coastal Algonquian scholarship.
Like his contemporary, Hudson Valley Indian specialist Edward Manning Ruttenber, Tooker was a passionate and talented amateur. Neither man was a university trained professional academician. Ruttenber, whose 1872 magnum opus, History of the Indian Tribes of Hudson's River, remains a standard reference work on the subject, was a Newburgh, New York printer. Tooker, for his part, was a Sag Harbor, Long Island pharmacist. Neither man was formally trained in linguistics or ethnology. Both, however, would come to exert strong influences on the early development of both fields in New York and New England. Like so many others before and since, Tooker's interest in Native Americans grew from a childhood fascination. Discovering Indian relics near his home in eastern Long Island, he soon began to hunt for stone tools and other evidences of Indian life in nearby farm fields and beaches. An avid and determined collector, he ultimately amassed a collection of more than 15,000 artifacts. Initially planning to study at Yale, circumstances forced him to enter the pharmaceutical trade in 1866.
Corresponding with specialists and studying in local libraries in his spare time, Tooker gradually gained a reputation as one of the foremost students of eastern Long Island Indian life. It was this reputation that finally led one of his correspondents to recommend Tooker to Herbert Foster Gunnison, editor of the Brooklyn Eagle Almanac, as the scholar most qualified to compile a list of Long Island Indian place names and their meanings for the paper in 1887. He published his first list one year later. Enthusiastically received by the Eagle's readers, Tooker's articles on Indian place names subsequently became a regular feature in the Almanac. Initially focusing upon Long Island names, Tooker's purview gradually expanded to include analyses of names from Nova Scotia to Virginia.
As the years passed, Tooker presented papers in front of scholarly organizations such as the American Association for the Advancement of Science. Continuing to write annual articles in the Brooklyn Eagle Almanac, Tooker also began to publish his work in such major scholarly journals as the American Anthropologist and the Archaeologist. In 1896, his first book, a study of New England missionary John Eliot's Indian interpreter, "Cockenoe de Long Island," was published by New York printer Francis P. Harper. This publication marked the beginning of an interest in Eliot's Indian linguistic research that would continue throughout the remaining years of his life.
In 1901, four years after any early retirement brought on by ill health, Francis P. Harper published ten of Tooker's major papers in a limited edition of bound monographs entitled the "Algonquian Series." Still consulted by specialists, the Algonquian Series represents a landmark in Coastal Algonquian studies. Each volume contains a tightly reasoned and well documented examination of a specific problem in ethnohistory or philology. The first of these, a 75 page essay on the "The Origin of the Name Manhattan," set the tone for exacting scholarship that marks the entire series. Tooker began by reviewing all available historic records and oral traditions relating to the place name. Surveying the vast body of literature devoted to the subject, he contrasted and assessed the validity of such widely varying translations as Moravian missionary John Heckewelder's "good place to collect bow wood," or "place of general inebriation," with other glosses such as pioneer ethnologist Henry Rowe Schoolcraft's "People of the Whirlpool." Working with Eliot's Natick materials and consulting other lexicons, Tooker came up with the translation "Hilly island" by combining the Delaware term for island, "mannah," with northern Algonquian suffix for hills, " atin."
These limited editions brought Tooker much fame among his small coterie of specialists. They did not, however, bring in much income. Worsening health and fiscal difficulties often dogged Tooker's declining years. He was forced to sell his Indian artifact collection to the Brooklyn Museum in 1901. Arthritis ultimately all but paralyzed him. Anxious to help him complete his life long goal, a book on Long Island Indian names, local patroness Mrs. Russel Sage established a trust fund for his support in 1906 or 1907. Nursed by his wife and aided by secretaries hired by Mrs. Sage, Tooker finally saw his last project into print in 1911. This volume, Indian Place Names on Long Island, has since become the classic study of its type, and, as such, the most lasting memorial to the scholarship of this pioneer Algonkinist.
Tooker had the great good fortune to publish the results of much of his research during his lifetime. His notes, document transcriptions, unpublished papers, proof sheets, and more than a few unpublished manuscripts have not yet seen print. Much of this material has been reproduced in the present microfilm edition. It contains unedited proof drafts of published papers, unpublished manuscripts of articles on a wide variety of topics, and transcriptions of large numbers of primary documents. Tooker's unpublished work on Eliot's Natick materials, which consumed much of his attention during his latter years, represents an important resource for future investigators. His transcripts of colonial manuscripts also have assumed an unanticipated significance since the destruction of many of the originals in the 1911 Albany capitol fire.
Collectively, the materials provide an important source for Coastal Algonquian ethnology, ethnohistory, and linguistics. They also furnish insights into the point of view and methods of a pioneering figure in regional studies. These insights can reveal information important to understanding both what Tooker produced in his lifetime, and what subsequent scholars will make of his work.
Some of Tooker's images are online here: http://www.tookerphotocollection.com (not affiliated with Cornell University)
CONTAINER LIST
- Printed guide and information, including card index (Folder 0)
- Indian geographical names on Long Island, New York. 19 leaves (Folder 1)
  Also available on Reel 1, Frame 20
- Algonquian names for the rainbow (manuscript). 4p. (Folder 2)
  Also available on Reel 1, Frame 40
- Notes on the Algonquian verb (after James Hammond Trumbull). 11p. (Folder 3)
  Also available on Reel 1, Frame 47
- Abstracts of the journals of Mr. Azariah Horton (Volume 4)
  Horton was a missionary to the Indians on Long Island, in the employ of "The Society in Scotland for Propagating Christian Knowledge." These journals were printed in "The Christian Monthly History, or An Account of the Revival and Progress of Religion, Abroad and at Home", published in Edinburgh in Scotland. These abstracts are intended to furnish names of places visited and persons mentioned mainly. Also some names of ministers in New England, selected from same publication, and copies of various Indian deeds. (O.B. Ackerly, February 1894). 42 leaves.
  Also available on Reel 1, Frame 60
- The Indian names of places in Brooklyn, Long Island, with their significations (Folder 5)
  (Manuscript and proof sheets) Published in the Brooklyn Eagle Almanac, 1893. 17p.
  Also available on Reel 1, Frame 111
- On the derivation of the name Manhattan (manuscript). 15p. (Folder 6)
  Also available on Reel 1, Frame 129
- The origin of the name Chesapeake (manuscript). 4p. (Folder 7)
  Also available on Reel 1, Frame 144
- Roger Williams vindicated, or an answer to "Keyhole for Roger Williams' Key". (manuscript). 13p. (Folder 8)
  Also available on Reel 1, Frame 148
- Rev. Robert Fordham, and His place in history. (Folder 9)
  Manuscript by William Wallace Tooker. (Read before the Sag Harbor Historical Society, April 1, 1902). Article on Nathan Fordham included. 17 leaves.
  Also available on Reel 1, Frame 162
- Vocabulary of the Massachusetts or Natick, from Eliot's Indian Bible. 144p. (Volume 10)
  Also available on Reel 1, Frame 178
- Manuscript in relation to the Montauks and the Boundary of the Shinnecocks and the Unkechaugs, 1665. 2p. (Folder 11)
  Also available on Reel 1, Frame 235
- The Montauk Indians at East Hampton, Long Island, 1723. (manuscript copy). 2p. (Folder 12)
  Also available on Reel 1, Frame 238
- Some supposed Indian names of places on Long Island, New York. (manuscript). 7p. (Folder 13)
  Also available on Reel 1, Frame 242
- The aboriginal terms for Long Island published in the Brooklyn Almanac, 1894. (manuscript and proof). 17 leaves. (Folder 14)
  Also available on Reel 1, Frame 249
- Was Southhampton, Long Island, New York, called by the Indians Agawom? (manuscript). 5 leaves. (Folder 15)
  Also available on Reel 1, Frame 269
- Vocabulary of the Massachusetts or Natick language taken from Eliot's Indian Bible. 36 leaves. (Folder 16)
  Also available on Reel 1, Frame 274
- Indian names of villages and streams from Capt. John Smith's map of Virginia. 51p. (Volume 17)
  Also available on Reel 1, Frame 311
- Strachey's "Dictionarie" of the Powhatan language, arranged alphabetically. 65p. (Volume 18)
  Also available on Reel 1, Frame 364
- The name Rappahannock in Virginia. (manuscript). 4p. (Folder 19)
  Also available on Reel 1, Frame 430
- The mystery of the name Pamunkey. (manuscript). Read before the American Association for the Advancement of Science, Section H. August 30, 1895. 9p. (Folder 20)
  Also available on Reel 1, Frame 435
- The name Chickahominy, its origin and etymology. (manuscript). 10p. (Folder 21)
  Also available on Reel 1, Frame 444
- The name Susquehanna, its origin and signification. 9p. (manuscript). (Folder 22)
  Also available on Reel 1, Frame 453
- Copies of deeds from Indian natives to Andrew Gib, or Gibb, November 1685, and May 1687, involving Little Neck. Brookhaven, Long Island. (Copies by O.B. Ackerly, 1892). 8p. (Folder 23)
  Also available on Reel 1, Frame 463
- Copy of the deed from the Indians to the Trustees of Huntington, 1702. (Copied by O.B. Ackerly, 1894). 2 leaves. (Folder 24)
  Also available on Reel 1, Frame 473
- Abstract of the title of William Trist Bailey to certain premises situate in the town of Islip, Suffolk County, and State of New York. New York 1888. 26p. (Folder 25)
  Also available on Reel 1, Frame 488
- The Kuskarawaokes of Captain John Smith. (manuscript). 8p. (Folder 26)
  Also available on Reel 1, Frame 514
- Notes regarding the name Nowedonah. (manuscript). 6p. (Folder 27)
  Also available on Reel 1, Frame 522
- Analysis of the claims of Southold, Long Island, for priority of settlement over Southampton, Long Island, and how they are disproved by the early records and contemporary manuscripts. (manuscript). 20 leaves. (Folder 28)
  Also available on Reel 1, Frame 532
- Analysis and meaning of some of the Indian geographical names of Suffolk County, New York. A paper read before the Suffolk County Teacher's Institute at Riverhead, May 3rd, 1883. (Folder 29)
  Printed in the Riverhead Weekly News, May 15th 1883. By William S. Pelletreau, A.M., transcriber of the Southampton Town records, historical writer, etc., etc., (1874). 20p.
  Also available on Reel 1, Frame 552
- Various Algonquian notes. 26p. (Volume 30)
  Also available on Reel 1, Frame 572
- Indian place names on Long Island, revised and corrected for the (Brooklyn Eagle) Almanac of 1890. (manuscript). 16p. (Folder 31)
  Also available on Reel 1, Frame 620
- Claims of Gardiners Island for priority of English settlement over any other locality on Long Island. (manuscript). 4p. (Folder 32)
  Also available on Reel 1, Frame 636
- An early mention of the Kuskarawaokes. (manuscript). 2p. (Folder 33)
  Also available on Reel 1, Frame 640
- Indian place names in East Hampton Town, Long Island, with their probable significations. (manuscript). 12p. (Folder 34)
  Also available on Reel 1, Frame 643
- Extracts from Indian deeds of 1649 1666 relating to lands on Long Island. Copied by (or for) George R. Howell. 2p. (Folder 35)
  Also available on Reel 1, Frame 655
- Letter and map from Thomas W. Bicknell regarding Sowams, 1904. 2p. (Folder 36)
  Also available on Reel 1, Frame 658
- Letter dated June 10, 1896, to James A. Canfield, respecting the name Patchogue. 3p. (Folder 37)
  Also available on Reel 1, Frame 660
- The Indian Fort on Montauk, Long Island, some historical and other facts relating thereto (Folder 38)
  Manuscript written for the express 8p.
  Also available on Reel 1, Frame 663
- Cobb, a farming district at Southampton, Long Island. The origin and signification of its name. (Folder 39)
  Manuscript written for the express 5p.
  Also available on Reel 1, Frame 672
- Dialect of the New Jersey Lenape. Obtained for Thomas Jefferson in 1792, at the Village of Edgpiiliik, West New Jersey. (Folder 40)
  Copy of the manuscript in the American Philosophical Society of Philadelphia.
  Also available on Reel 1, Frame 678
- Indian geographic names, and why we should study them. Illustrated by some Rhode Island examples. (manuscript). 1897. 17 leaves. (Folder 41)
  Also available on Reel 1, Frame 682
- Copies of Indian deeds of 1661, 1670, 1687. Place names: Martha's Vinyard, Westchester County. Notes on Eliot's Bible. 31p. (Volume 42)
  Also available on Reel 1, Frame 699
- Vocabulary of the Montauk Tribe (1798) (Folder 43)
  Copied February 12th, 1890, from the original contained in an old memorandum book written by John Lyon (Lion) Gardiner, Esq., the 7th proprietor of Gardiners Island, now in the possession of his grandson, J. Lyon Gardiner, the 12th proprietor. Sag Harbor, New York. 2p.
  Also available on Reel 1, Frame 729
- Letters from Harry Andrew Wright of Springfield, Massachusetts (Folder 44)
  To William Wallace Tooker, in 1903, regarding Algonquian proper names in New England, with some notes thereon by Tooker. 53p.
  Also available on Reel 1, Frame 731
- Extracts from Eliot's Indian Bible (Volume A)
  Many taken from the copy in the possession of John Lyon Gardiner, Esq., the 12th proprietor of Gardiner's Island. 204p.
  Also available on Reel 1, Frame 783
- Natick English dictionary compiled from Eliot's Bible. (Volume B)
  Undated, handwritten manuscript, acquired February 1919. 205p.
  Also available on Reel 1, Frame 893